Marc'Aurelio Ranzato

Facebook Inc. 770 Broadway New York, NY 10003, USA email: ranzatomr@gmail.com

 $web:\ https://ranzato.github.io/$

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My primary research interests are in the area of machine learning, with applications to computer vision, natural language processing and speech recognition. In particular, I have been investigating methods to learn representations of data in a fully unsupervised, semi-supervised, and continual learning settings.

I have been working with deep learning methods, energy based models and graphical models. I have designed algorithms for various applications, such as object recognition in natural images, machine translation, summarization and acoustic modeling for speech recognition.

CURRENT APPOINTMENT

Facebook Inc., New York, NY - USA Position: *Manager Research Scientist* Period: September 2013 to present

EDUCATION

New York University, The Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences, New York, NY, U.S.A.

Ph.D. degree in Computer Science, May 2009

Advisor: Prof. Yann LeCun

Thesis: Unsupervised learning of feature hierarchies

Committee: Rob Fergus, Geoffrey Hinton, Yann LeCun, Sebastian Seung, Eero Simoncelli

University of Padova, Padova, Italy

Laurea in Electronics Engineering, April 2004 110/110 cum laude

Advisor: Prof. Pietro Perona and Prof. Ruggero Frezza

Thesis: Automatic recognition of biological particles in microscopic images

Conservatory "Frescobaldi", Ferrara, Italy

Diploma of music in violin, June 1999 9/10

ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

University of Toronto, Department of Computer Science, Toronto, ON - CANADA

Position: Post-Doctoral Fellow Supervisor: Prof. Geoffrey Hinton Period: July 2009 to June 2011 Project: "Learning gated MRF's"

California Institute of Technology, Computer Vision Laboratory, Pasadena, CA, U.S.A.

Position: Graduate Research Assistant

Supervisor: Prof. Pietro Perona

Period: August 2003 - March 2004, July 2004 - August 2004 Project: "Automatic Visual Recognition of Biological Particles"

WORK EXPERIENCE

Google Inc., Mountain View, CA - USA

Position: Research Scientist

Period: October 2011 to September 2013

Yahoo! Research, Mission College, Santa Clara, CA, U.S.A.

Position: Summer Intern

Host: Kilian Weinberger, Malcolm Slaney, Olivier Chapelle, Kishore Papineni

Period: Summer 2008

Project: Learning sparse and locally shift-invariant feature hierarchies of images

Microsoft Research LTD., Cambridge, U.K.

Position: Summer Intern Host: Martin Szummer Period: Summer 2007

Project: Learning semantic representations of text documents from partially labeled collections

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant, New York University

Graduate Course on Machine Learning, Fall 2007. Instructor: Prof. LeCun

Tutorials and Guest Lectures

- Graduate Course on Machine Learning for Natural Language, Spring 2018, Harvard University Instructor: Prof. Alexander Rush
- Tutorial on Deep Learning for Vision, Text and Sequences. DeepLearn Summer School, Bilbao 2017.
- Graduate Course on Deep Learning, Spring 2017, New York University Instructor: Prof. Yann LeCun.
- Graduate Course on Computer Vision CS 231A, Winter 2014. Stanford University Instructor: Prof. Savarese.
- CVPR 2014 Tutorial on Deep Learning
- CVPR 2013 Tutorial on Large Scale Visual Recognition
- ICML 2013 Tutorial on Deep Learning, jointly with Y. LeCun

- UCLA IPAM Summer School 2012 on Deep Learning
- CVPR 2012 Tutorial on Deep Learning
- Graduate Course on Advanced Machine Learning, Spring 2010. University of Toronto Instructor: Prof. Zemel.
- CIFAR Summer School, 2010.

Students Advised

- Guillaume Lample (Fall 2016 till present, Ph.D. advisor)
- Yoon Kim (summer 2017, internship at Facebook)
- Sam Wiseman (summer 2016 and summer 2017, internship at Facebook)
- Sebastien Jean (summer 2015, internship at Facebook)
- Gregoire Mesnil (summer 2014 internship at Facebook)
- Babak Shakibi (winter 2014 internship at Facebook)
- David Eigen (summer 2013 internship at Google)
- Matthew D. Zeiler (summer 2012 internship at Google)

Students Co-Advised

- Sida Wang (University of Toronto)

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

Guest Editor for the International Journal of Computer Vision Special Issue on "Deep Learning", jointly with G.E. Hinton and Y. LeCun

Workshop Organizer

- Deep Learning Sympsium
 - Conference: Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS) 2015
- Tutorial on Deep Learning for Computer Vision
 - Conference: Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR) 2014
- Representation Learning
 - Conference: International Conference of Machine Learning (ICML) 2012
 - Co-oranizers: Aaron Courville, Hugo Larochelle, Yoshua Bengio
- Challenges in Learning Hierarchical Models: Transfer Learning and Optimization Conference: Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS) 2011
 - Co-oranizers: Quoc V. Le, Ruslan Salakhutdinov, Andrew Ng, Josh Tenenbaum
- Deep Learning and Unsupervised Feature Learning
 - Conference: Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS) 2010
 - Co-organizers: Honglak Lee, Yoshua Bengio, Geoffrey Hinton, Yann LeCun, Andrew Y. Ng

Program Chair

- International Conference on Learning Representations 2017
- International Conference on Learning Representations 2018

Area Chair

• International Conference of Machine Learning 2018

- Neural Information Processing Systems 2017
- Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition 2016
- International Conference of Computer Vision 2015
- Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition 2015
- Neural Information Processing Systems 2014
- International Conference of Machine Learning 2014
- ACM Multimedia 2014
- Neural Information Processing Systems 2013
- International Conference of Machine Learning 2013
- Neural Information Processing Systems 2012
- International Conference of Machine Learning 2012
- Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence 2012

Reviewer

- Neural Computation
- Journal of Machine Learning
- IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence
- International Journal of Computer Vision
- International Journal of Machine Learning and Cybernetics
- Neural Information Processing Systems
- International Conference on Learning Representations
- International Conference of Machine Learning
- Artificial Intelligence and Statistics
- Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition
- Eurepean Conference of Computer Vision
- International Conference of Computer Vision
- Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining
- AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence
- Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence

HONORS

- Top-100 most influential scholars in Machine Learning for the year of 2016 according to AMiner.
- NYU Dean's dissertation fellowship, 2008-2009
- "Henry M. MacCracken" Award Scholarship, 2004-2008
- "Ing. Aldo Gini" Award for Italian researchers abroad, 2004

- S. Edunov, M. Ott, M. Auli, D. Grangier and M. Ranzato, Classical Structured Prediction Losses for Sequence to Sequence Learning. North America Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL) 2018
- G. Lample, A. Conneau, L. Denoyer and M. Ranzato Unsupervised Machine Translation Using Monolingual Corpora Only. International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) 2018
- A. Conneau, G. Lample, M. Ranzato, L. Denoyer and H. JÄl'gou, Word translation without parallel data. International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) 2018
- S. Gross, M. Ranzato and A. Szlam, Hard Mixtures of Experts for Large Scale Weakly Supervised Vision. Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2017
- D. Lopez-Paz and M. Ranzato, Gradient Episodic Memory for Continual Learning. Neural Processing Information (NIPS) 2017
- G. Lample, N. Zeghidour, N. Usunier, A. Bordes, L. Denoyer and M. Ranzato, Fader networks: Manipulating images by sliding attributes. Neural Processing Information (NIPS) 2017
- S. Chintala, M. Ranzato, A. Szlam, Y. Tian, M. Tygert and W. Zaremba *Scale-invariant learning and convolutional networks*. Applied and Computational Harmonic Analysis 42 (1), 154-166 2017
- J. Li, A.H. Miller, S. Chopra, M. Ranzato and J. Weston Learning through dialogue interactions. International Conference on Learning Representations (IC LR) 2017
- J. Li, A.H. Miller, S. Chopra, M. Ranzato and J. Weston *Dialogue learning with human-in-the-loop*. International Conference on Learning Representations (IC LR) 2017
- M. Ranzato, S. Chopra, M. Auli and W. Zaremba, Sequence level training with recurrent neural networks. International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) 2016
- Y. Taigman, M. Yang, M. Ranzato and L. Wolf, Web-scale training for face identification. Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2015
- T. Mikolov, A. Joulin, S. Chopra, M. Mathieu and M. Ranzato, Learning Longer Memory in Recurrent Neural Networks, in International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2015
- Y. Taigman, M. Yang, M. Ranzato and L. Wolf, *DeepFace: Closing the Gap to Human-Level Performance in Face Verification*, in IEEE Proc. of Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition Conference (CVPR), 2014
- N. Zhang, M. Paluri, M. Ranzato, T. Darrell and L. Bourdev, PANDA: Pose Aligned Networks for Deep Attribute Modeling, in IEEE Proc. of Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition Conference (CVPR), 2014
- M. Ranzato, J. Susskind, V. Mnih and G.E. Hinton, On Deep Generative Models with Applications to Recognition, in IEEE Proc. of Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition Conference (CVPR), 2011

- M. Denil, B. Shakibi, L. Dinh, **M. Ranzato**, N. de Freitas, *Predicting Parameters in Deep Learning*, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS), MIT Press, 2013
- A. Frome, G. Corrado, J. Shlens, S. Bengio, J. Dean, M. Ranzato, T. Mikolov, *DeViSE: A Deep Visual-Semantic Embedding Model*, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS), MIT Press, 2013
- M.D. Zeiler, M. Ranzato, R. Monga, M. Mao, K. Yang, Q.V. Le, P. Nguyen, A. Senior, V. Vanhoucke, J. Dean, G.E. Hinton, On Rectified Linear Units for Speech Processing, International Conference on Acoustic, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2013
- A. Senior, G. Heigold, M. Ranzato, K. Yang, An Empirical Study of Learning Rates in Deep Neural Networks for Speech Recognition, International Conference on Acoustic, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2013
- G. Heigold, V. Vanhoucke, A. Senior, P. Nguyen, M. Ranzato, M. Devin, J. Dean, *Multilingual Acoustic Models using Distributed Neep Neural Networks*, International Conference on Acoustic, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2013
- J. Dean, G. Corrado, R. Monga, K. Chen, M. Devin, Q.V. Le, M. Mao, M. Ranzato, A. Senior, P. Tucker, K. Yang, A.Y. Ng, *Large Scale Distributed Deep Networks*, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS), MIT Press, 2012
- Q.V. Le, M. Ranzato, R. Monga, M. Devin, G. Corrado, K. Chen, J. Dean, A.Y. Ng, Building High-Level Features Using Large Scale Unsupervised Learning, International Conference of Machine Learning (ICML), 2012.
- K. Swersky, M. Ranzato, D. Buchman, B.M. Marlin, N. de Freitas, On Autoencoders and Score Matching for Energy Based Models, International Conference of Machine Learning (ICML), 2011.
- M. Ranzato, J. Susskind, V. Mnih and G.E. Hinton, On Deep Generative Models with Applications to Recognition, in IEEE Proc. of Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition Conference (CVPR), 2011
- M. Ranzato, V. Mnih and G.E. Hinton, Generating More Realistic Images Using Gated MRF's, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS), MIT Press, 2010
- G. Dahl, M. Ranzato, A. Mohamed and G.E. Hinton, *Phone Recognition with the Mean-Covariance Restricted Boltzmann Machine*, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS), MIT Press, 2010
- M. Ranzato and G.E. Hinton, *Modeling Pixel Means and Covariances Using Factorized Third-Order Boltzmann Machines*, in IEEE Proc. of Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition Conference (CVPR), 2010
- M. Ranzato, A. Krizhevsky and G.E. Hinton, Factored 3-Way Restricted Boltzmann Machines for Modeling Natural Images, in Proc. of the 13-th International Workshop on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), 2010
- K. Jarrett, K. Kavukcuoglu, M. Ranzato and Y. LeCun, What is the Best Multi-Stage Architecture for Object Recognition?, in IEEE Proc. of International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV), 2009

- K. Kavukcuoglu, M. Ranzato, R. Fergus, Y. LeCun, Learning Invariant Features through Topographic Filter Maps, in IEEE Proc. of Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition Conference (CVPR), 2009
- M. Ranzato, M. Szummer, Semi-supervised Learning of Compact Document representations with Deep Networks, International Conference of Machine Learning (ICML), 2008.
- M. Ranzato, Y. Boureau, Y. LeCun, Sparse Feature Learning for Deep Belief Networks, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS), MIT Press, 2007
- M. Ranzato, Y. LeCun, A Sparse and Locally Shift Invariant Feature Extractor Applied to Document Images, International Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition (ICDAR), 2007.
- Y. LeCun, S. Chopra, M. Ranzato, F.J. Huang, Energy-Based Models in Document Recognition and Computer Vision, International Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition (ICDAR), 2007.
- M. Ranzato, F.J. Huang, Y. Boureau, Y. LeCun, Unsupervised Learning of Invariant Feature Hierarchies with Applications to Object Recognition, in IEEE Proc. of Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition Conference (CVPR), 2007
- M. Ranzato, Y. Boureau, S. Chopra, Y. LeCun, A Unified Energy-Based Framework for Unsupervised Learning, In Proc. of the 11-th International Workshop on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), 2007
- M. Ranzato, C.S. Poultney, S. Chopra, Y. LeCun, Efficient Learning of Sparse Representations with an Energy-Based Model, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS), MIT Press, 2006

JOURNAL PAPERS

- M. Ranzato, V. Mnih, J. Susskind, G.E. Hinton, *Modeling Natural Images Using Gated MRFs*. IEEE Trans. Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence, 2013.
- M. Ranzato, P.E. Taylor, J.M. House, R.C. Flagan, Y. LeCun, P. Perona, *Automatic recognition of biological particles in microscopic images*. Pattern Recognition Letters, Vol. 28, Issue 1, 1 Jan. 2007, pp. 31-39.

OTHER PUBLICATIONS AND TECHNICAL REPORTS

- S. Wiseman, S. Chopra, M. Ranzato, A. Szlam, R. Sun, S. Chintala and N. Vasilache, Training Language Models Using Target-Propagation. arXiv:1702.047702017
- J. Van Amersfoort, A. Kannan, M. Ranzato, A. Szlam, D. Tran and S. Chintala, *Transformation-based models of video sequences*. arXiv:1701.08435 2016
- M. Tygert, A. Szlam, S. Chintala, M. Ranzato, Y. Tian, W. Zaremba, Convolutional networks and learning invariant to homogeneous multiplicative scalings. arXiv:1506.08230 2015
- M. Ranzato, A. Szlam, J. Bruna, M. Mathieu, R. Collobert and S. Chopra, Video (Language)
 Modeling: A Baseline for Generative Models of Natural Videos, arXiv:1412.6604 2015

- M. Ranzato On Learning Where To Look, ArXiv:1405.5488 2014
- K. Kavukcuoglu, M. Ranzato, Y. LeCun, Fast Inference in Sparse Coding Algorithms with Applications to Object Recognition, CBLL Technical Report December 2008, arXiv 1010.3467
- Y. LeCun, S. Chopra, R. Hadsell, M. Ranzato, F.J. Huang, A Tutorial on Energy-Based Learning, in Bakir et al. (eds) "Predicting Structured Outputs", MIT Press 2006

WORKSHOP AND DEMONSTRATION PAPERS

- G. Mesnil, T. Mikolov, M. Ranzato, Y. Bengio, Ensemble of Generative and Discriminative Techniques for Sentiment Analysis of Movie Reviews, workshop at the International Conference on Representation Learning (ICLR), 2015
- D. Eigen, I. Sutskever, M. Ranzato, Learning Factored Representations in a Deep Mixture of Experts, workshop at the International Conference on Representation Learning (ICLR), 2014
- O. Yadan, K. Adams, Y. Taigman, M. Ranzato Multi-GPU Training of ConvNets, workshop at the International Conference on Representation Learning (ICLR), 2014
- E. Horster, M. Slaney, M. Ranzato, K. Weinberger, *Unsupervised Image Ranking*, Proc. of the first ACM workshop on Large-scale multimedia retriaval and mining, Beijing, China, 2009
- K. Kavukcuoglu, M. Ranzato, Y. LeCun, Fast Inference in Sparse Coding Algorithms with Applications to Object Recognition, "Optimization for Machine Learning" workshop at Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS), 2008
- D.R. Edgington, I. Kerkez, D.E. Cline, **M. Ranzato**, P. Perona, *Detecting, Tracking and Classifying Animals in Underwater Video*, IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), demonstration, New York, New York, 2006
- D.R. Edgington, I. Kerkez, D.E. Cline, D. Oliver, M. Ranzato, P. Perona, *Detecting, Tracking and Classifying Animals in Underwater Video*, IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), demonstration, San Diego, California, 2005

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

- Deep Learning for Vision
 - workshop on Web-Scale Vision and Social Media at CVPR 2014
 - Workshop on Scene Understanding at CVPR 2014
 - Large Scale Visual Recognition tutorial at CVPR 2014
 - Large Scale Visual Recognition tutorial at CVPR 2013
 - Bay Area Vision Meeting 2013
- On The Quest For Good Generative Models of Natural Images
 - CIFAR NCAP Workshop, Vancouver, Canada, December 2010
 - CBLL seminar, New York University, New York, November 2010
- Modeling Natural Images with Higher-Order Boltzmann Machines

- CIFAR Summer School, Toronto, Canada, August 2010
- Redwood Center for Theoretical Neuroscience, June 2010
- Computer Science Department, Stanford, June 2010
- Google Research, Mountain View, June 2010
- Department of Computer Science, University of California, San Diego, June 2010
- Department of Computer Science, University of California, Irvine, June 2010
- CIFAR NCAP Workshop, Vancouver, Canada, December 2009
- High-Accuracy Object Recognition with a New Convolutional Net Architecture and Learning Algorithm, Learning Workshop, Snowbird Clearwater, April 2009
- Unsupervised Learning of Sparse and Invariant Features Hierarchies, Learning Workshop, Snowbird - Puerto Rico, March 2007
- Efficient Learning of Sparse Representations with an Energy-Based Model
 - Computational Vision Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, December 2006
 - Laboratory for Computational Vision, Center for Neuroscence NYU, October 2006
- Energy-Based Model for Unsupervised Learning of Sparse Overcomplete Representations
 - Learning Workshop, Snowbird Utah, April 2006
 - CIAR NCAP Workshop, Vancouver Canada, December 2005

OTHER MEETINGS

- Workshop: Mathematics of Knowledge and Search Engines Workshops II: Numerical Tools and Fast Algorithms for Massive Data Mining, Search Engines and Applications, IPAM UCLA, October 2007.
- Graduate Summer School: Neural Computation and Adaptive Perception, CIAR University of Toronto, August 2006.
- NESCAI Cornell University, Ithaca, April 2006.
- Graduate Summer School: Intelligent Extraction of Information from Graphs and High Dimensional Data, IPAM UCLA, July 2005.

PATENTS

- M. Ranzato, K.Q. Weinberger, E. Hoerster, M. Slaney. System and method for improved classification. US Patent 9,639,7802017
- J. Shlens, Q.V. Le, G.S. Corrado, M. Ranzato. Generating labeled images. US Patent 9,256,80712016
- A.W. Senior, M. Ranzato. Curriculum learning for speech recognition. US Patent 9,202,464
- M. Ranzato. Identifying objects in images. US Patent 9,129,190

- \bullet Y. Taigman, M. Yang, **M. Ranzato**. Systems and methods for facial representation. US Patent App. $14/530,\!585$
- P. Perona, **M. Ranzato**, R. Flagan. Automatic visual recognition of biological particles. US Patent App. 11/122,575 US Patent 9,202,464